well how far would you go to tell the
truth that's the question posed by a
remarkable new documentary called
silenced which just premiered at the
Tribeca Film Festival it it follows
three National Security whistleblowers
who fight to reveal the darkest corners
of America's war on terror challenging a
government that is increasingly
determined to maintain secrecy as it
expands its powers they are former
justice department lawyer jessyn Rak
former uh senior NSA official Thomas
Drake and the former CIA officer John
kako the film depicts the extraordinary
lens the government traversed to wreak
havoc on their personal lives through a
sustained campaign of intimidation and
harassment this is the trailer for
silence part of the purpose of doing
what they've been doing for the last
several
years is to destroy
you I never thought of myself as a
whistleblower sometimes I go back and
forth in my mind mind where I wish I had
kept my mouth shut and other times I
wish that I had shouted it from the
rooftops there is information that the
public in a functioning democracy has a
right to know Thomas Jefferson said that
an informed citizenry is the crucial
part of the Democracy I took an oath I
had to deal with a government who was in
violation of the oath and I couldn't
remain silent I could not live with
myself knowing that another human being
could be put to death because I kept my
mouth shut sh would you call it torture
water boarding is probably something
that we shouldn't be in the business of
doing I was the first CIA officer to
confirm the use of torture techniques
against Al-Qaeda prisoners our country
had instituted a torture policy and we
ran head into that you're supposed to
accept these things as normal because to
the people who have been there it is
completely normal NSA would now
instrument the United States of America
for the purposes of draget blanket
electronic surveillance on a v
scale I explained the facts of my case
to my lawyer he said wow you meet the
classic textbook definition of a
whistleblower we're people who join the
government for all the good reasons work
for a number of years and then confront
something that just stops US the White
House has approved it it's all legal as
soon as he said it's all legal the hair
stood up on the back of my
neck they began asking me questions well
I've spent my entire adult life working
with the FBI so the FBI needs my help
I'm happy to help he looked at the file
and said very matter of factly this file
has been purged they're now engaged in
an active cover up at the highest levels
it wasn't until I was about an hour into
this interview that I realized wait a
minute they're investigating me the
apparatus of the US government was
turned against me every phone call
you've ever made emails you've ever sent
your bank statements tax records I was
trying to be honest and obey the law and
yet I'm the one who ends up having to
hire a team of lawyers they set the
target they put the bullseye on me and
said we're going to make an example of
him I have to try to protect my children
from being exposed to it I've got the
FBI surveilling me on and off for the
last 7 months you have to mortgage your
house you have to empty your bank
account I've applied for every job I can
think of haven't gotten even an email or
a call back the people that you used to
work with turned against you your
neighbors are at least suspicious
because it's not every day that
government investigators are knocking on
their doors what has now happened to my
family it's a very tormented existence
you're not loyal you're not a good
American you're a terrorist sympathizer
that secrecy regime despite President
Obama's pledges of transparency and
openness has only continued to
expand I'm not the pushover that these
guys think I am I'm as tough as they are
and I'm going to
fight that trailer for the new
documentary silence just premiered at
Tribeca Film Festival we're joined by
the film's director James spon he's
previous documentary incident in new
Baghdad was nominated for an Academy
Award welcome to democracy Now talk
about why you chose these three people
Tom Drake jesselyn radak as well as John
kyaku um thank you for having me by the
way um well um I really making my
previous film incident new Baghdad was
already this was on my radar of course
that film was made possible because of
that footage released by Wikileaks and
we now know it was Chelsea Manning who
who released this footage of of an
Apache helicopter attack in in
Baghdad and uh so that got me to
thinking about this whole you know who
controls the information who's allowed
to release it and who's not what what is
the American public allowed to see and
and and what aren't they allowed to see
and who are the people who kind of
have the courage to step up and say wait
a minute when the whole bureaucracy is
going another Direction they say well
well I'm not sure about this you know
and and uh dissenting against uh what's
the the common practice uh so I thought
well these are kind of rare individuals
and I want to learn more about them and
and that's when I started researching uh
the people in
my